Kia ora.
Thank you very much for joining us.
Do you have any colleagues who are coming, or is it-
Just me.
Okay, great. Thank you so much for being here.
I didn't mean to suggest that was not enough.
We are very, very happy to see you, and thank you for making your time available.
This works well if you just take a couple of minutes to introduce yourself to the
committee.
We are familiar with the documents that have been exchanged back and forth, but it
would just help to sort of hear you contextualize it for a bit, and then we will
definitely have some follow-up questions for you on the particular issues.
Okay. So shall I introduce myself?
Please.
Okay.
Ko Tara toku maunga. Ko Boin toku awa. Nō Airanna ahau.
E noho ana ahau ki te whanganui a Tara.
Kei te mahi ahau i te Pōwhiri o ngā Kai Mataiwātu me ngā Kaiwhakarato Mōhitet.
Ko taku tūranga Tumu Whakarae me te Koutou. Tena koutou. Tena koutou.
Tena koutou katoa.
Kia ora.
So briefly, I explained my mountain, my river,
that I'm from Ireland, currently living in Wellington, working with the
Optometrists and Dispensing Opticians Board as chief executive and registrar, and
my name is Suzanne Halpin, and I'm very pleased to see you all.
Thank you, Suzanne. Really appreciate it.
Would you like to tell us a little bit about your fee structure, or do you want to
move straight to questions?
I guess I'll just give some background in relation to the fee structure, but I will
focus on the fees that are at issue here, being the
fee for accreditation, reaccreditation, and the fee for
those practitioners who are practicing under supervision.
So the background, first of all, starting with the accreditation/reaccreditation
fee. The background to that fee is that,
and I guess the reasons for it being described in the way that it has, relate to
the
accreditation activities that the board undertakes and the guidance
that was published around that in 2022,
in which the fact that there would be costs associated and would be invoiced to
the relevant
institution were set out as it being cost recovery.
Subsequently, that fee was gazetted just last year out
of, I guess, an abundance of caution to ensure that the board was properly
gazetting the fees that it charged.
With regards to the reasons for the cost recovery basis,
those reasons relate to the
variability and the frequency in which the board
undertakes these activities, making setting an actual fee amount,
I guess,
difficult. There are differences in
whether a matter is relating to an accreditation or
reaccreditation of an institute or program, whether that program is an existing
program for an existing provider, a new program, whether it's
postgraduate or undergraduate, the location of the provider
itself, and where the site visit for the accreditation process would take
place.
Looking at the
fees set by other RAs, it seemed to us that
where there are set fees, there's quite variability in the fees
that are set, possibly for the same reasons that this board
was encountering potential difficulty, and there was
wide variation where fees were set.
Our view at the time was that, and continued to be until receiving the letter from
the committee, was that a cost recovery basis seemed like the fairer
approach given the extent of the variability and the
difficulty in setting a fee.
It also seemed, to us at the time, to be consistent
with the Officer of the Auditor General's guidance in relation to fees set by
organizations.
So that's the accreditation fee.
In relation to the fee for supervision or practitioners practicing under
supervision, the reason for adopting a cost recovery
model in that instance, again,
it was to allow the
practitioner and potential supervisors to
be able to determine the fees amongst themselves and also to give the option that
the supervisor and the practitioner could come to their own arrangement.
Typically, the way it happens, and the way it has happened, with regards to those
fees,
is that the practitioner who is going to be
requiring to be supervised would be offered the opportunity to nominate a
supervisor that the board would then be asked to approve.
And in most cases, the board has approved that person.
So
again, to give, I guess, the flexibility and the opportunity for practitioners
to be able to
manage that aspect of the requirements themselves.
Suzanne, do you mind if I ask, with the accreditation part
of the fee setting that you undertook, so that was gazetted only last year.
What was the situation before? It was never gazetted. Was it? Right.
It was never gazetted. The fee was described in our accreditation guidelines,
but it was never gazetted. And
prior to last year, the most recent accreditation or
reaccreditation activity happened in 2022.
Okay.
And prior to that it was 2017.
Right. So they're just not that common.
It was just not that common. Another reason why it sort of was difficult for us to
sort of gauge where our fees should be set and what would be an appropriate amount,
and even at this point,
there is an accreditation process that is underway at the moment,
and it's for a provider in Australia, but it's to do with an existing
program. We don't have recent experience of
conducting an accreditation for a new program and a new provider.
Understood. And so the fee that you're likely to be sitting
near, is insignificant, I would imagine.
Can you give us a ballpark figure of what sort of fee you charged?
Again, it's cost recovery. So in this particular
instance-
Yeah
... using this as an example-
... what the charges passed on to the provider would be will include things like
the cost of flights and accommodation for our accreditation review team
Yeah. And I think was it $500? Was it $50,000? Was it how many dollars?
Oh,
the previous accreditation,
that
was completed in 2022. The costs were circa
$10,000.
Okay.
But prior to that, there was an accreditation that was supposed to have taken place
for an organization in the UK, and that process had commenced before
it was stopped because the provider then decided that they didn't want to be
reaccredited. And
at a very early stage in the program,
we had outlaid costs of $15,000
just on flights. The provider wanted to arrange accommodation for the
AOR team itself, so we weren't going to have to manage those costs.
Okay.
But as it turned out in that instance, we were able to recover costs for the
flights when the review didn't take place because we recovered money from the
airline. So we then only had to seek recovery of the portion of the flight cost
that we hadn't been able to recover from the airline, which was in and around
$5,000, just from memory.
Just, sorry to rush the question-
No, you're okay
... because we're at the end of time.
Can I ask you, on the practitioners under supervision-
Mm-hmm
... the question that the committee has got to ask itself is you have been asked to
set a fee, and whether you have complied with the requirements of the legislation
to set a fee. If, A, the fee is unknown, and B, the
invoice is not,
you don't even see the invoice.
Mm-hmm.
So my question to you is,
do you think that that meets the definition of prescriber fee?
Well,
prior to the
notification from the review committee, that was the case.
Okay. So you're indicating you're open to hearing from us on a sort of-
Yeah.
Okay. Great. Thank you.
Yeah, and that
goes for the accreditation fee as well.
So as I say,
our interpretation at the time was that we were consistent, or rather we were not
inconsistent. Describing fees on a cost recovery basis was
aligned from what we had seen from our fellow regulators as well.
So there was nothing to indicate to us at the time that that wasn't appropriate.
Okay.
But always open to feedback and to hearing from the committee.
That's, as I say, not going to be an issue.
Okay. That's helpful. One question from Miles.
The accreditation team that you have, where do they come from?
Are they overseas based? Are they New Zealand based?
They would be New Zealand based.
Thank you. I guess that's a helpful question.
Just Suzanne, general question for you,
where in the system is the incentive for you to make sure that
your costs are low? How do you hold yourselves to
a high standard on that?
How do we do that? Well,
we're always mindful of that. For example, in that most recent accreditation
that took place, from what I can see of the records, the education institute
was invoiced for flights, accommodation, and costs, but it didn't appear
that they were invoiced for the secretariat staff time.
And also, in relation to the
reaccreditation review that didn't take place, we made efforts to recover
the costs for the canceled flights from the airline rather than putting all of
those costs onto the provider.
Mm. Okay.
So we are always mindful that
where money is coming from and who is going to be essentially paying the
costs for the work that we do, and that is the practitioners that are registered
with the board, and it's also the providers of programs that, and
qualifications are being prescribed.
So, we make as much as possible, every effort that we can to keep
that in mind, and also to ensure that one set
of stakeholders is not, as much as is practicable, supporting
another set of stakeholders. And-
Just as a final, very, very brief question, and then we'll have to wrap this up.
Yeah.
Do you have a sense of, if someone is under supervision, what might they pay
in terms of a fee? Do you have any idea of an example in your mind?
We're just trying to contextualize it for ourselves.
Yeah.
Typically,
I believe, now this is anecdotally, but I believe that oftentimes because
the supervision can take place within the practitioner's workplace and is often
provided for by a manager or colleague, there is no charge to the
practitioner. However, it might not always be a case that that could be
accommodated within a practitioner's workplace.
So there might have to be another practitioner from another practice, another
location that would need to be engaged to provide the role of
supervisor. In that instance, it wouldn't necessarily always be the case that that
practitioner would be happy to not
receive a fee.
Great. Thank you so much. Thank you for joining us.
Okay.
We'll be in touch with some more written correspondence, and you're free to respond
to that as well.
Okay. Thank you for your time.
Thank you, Suzanne. Thank you.
And good luck to you all. Take care. Bye.
Bye.